[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
right boom welcome to stoa everyone
i am peter limberg the steward of the
stoa and the stow is a place for us to
cohere and dialogue about what matters
most at the knife's edge
of this very moment and for those of you
who are new
at the stoa uh sometimes we call it a
digital campfire
sometimes we call it a communal podcast
we have a
wisdom gym here uh and it's basically a
space where we have zoom events
essentially
uh we started uh when kovid first came
online
and we probably have around 400 uh
events
uh thus far all been for free and we
have an amazing guest like daniel
schmachtenberger or james cars from
finite infinite games and even noam
chomsky's coming on in november
and it's sort of becoming a hub this
kind of like indie hub of sense making
that all the cool kids come to escape
the culture war noise
uh and today we got brett weinstein
coming in i gotta play that that hype
that hype sound the next time the
hypeborn
um so brett is here today uh he's gonna
talk about unity 2020
and uh our for today is everyone's
favorite blackbird
ravenconnelly um so raven will introduce
uh brett and the
kind of question answer protocols and
raven was a former student of bret too i
don't know if people know that she was
uh they were evergreen together
so that's an exciting stoa trevory
trivia for everyone
so that being said i will uh allow
everyone to unmute themselves
please don't abuse that function and i
will take raven in
excellent thank you peter great yes i am
a former student of brett's at the
evergreen state college and for those of
you who don't know
um brett has a phd in evolutionary
biology and evolutionary theory
um and is a professor in exile from
evergreen
and he's the host of the dark horse
podcast and the mastermind
and advocate for the unity 2020
presidential campaign which is what we
are here to talk about today
so just before i hand it over to brett
and ask him a few questions we'll go
over the question and answer kind of
protocol
so i'm going to ask brett a few
questions to get us going today for
about
25 minutes we'll have a little bit of a
back and forth and then we'll move
into question and answer with the
audience where you can put your
questions for brett in the chat and then
i will call your name
you can mute yourself ask a question and
you get one
back and forth with with him so thank
you so much brett
for being here today thanks for having
me i'm excited about this
oh that sounded like there was an echo
oh maybe it's gone okay good great just
uh
yeah we don't i don't hear anything so
it should be good
um let's just like get to the basics
start off everybody
uh what is unity 2020 and why is this an
important movement
for this particular political campaign
so unity 2020 is a
proposal that i unveiled most
prominently
on joe rogan's podcast and it's
basically an attempt
to defeat the central argument that the
duopoly uses to keep us all prisoner
so the central argument is the lesser
evil
paradox that is to say you have to vote
for whatever the duopoly is
offering you because if you offer
something else
you will tend to empower the party that
is farther away from
what you want you will draw votes away
from that which is closer and therefore
the system will move away from your
desires rather than towards them
so that argument has kept us captive for
well basically for most of my adult life
all of those of us who
would entertain some alternative to the
toxic and corrupt duopoly
always seek for something over in
third-party space and it never works out
and we're always told that we are
betraying our values so the proposal
is to draft two candidates one from the
left and one from the right
and to draft them under the agreement
that they will govern together
as a team by consensus once elected
the person at the top of the ticket will
be chosen by
coin flip after four years their
positions will reverse and the person
who
was in the role of president will run
for the vice presidential slot and vice
versa
and this can continue until somebody has
been president twice at which point they
would have to be
replaced with a suitable alternative
candidate
and that could go on indefinitely the
idea of course
is to challenge the corruption that has
overtaken our system
and give people a choice to vote for
something
patriotic and decent i laid out three
characteristics that would be required
of all candidates we would consider
drafting
they have to be courageous they have to
be capable
and they have to be patriots and nothing
else
so that's the proposal and we are now uh
fairly deeply into this process
we went through nominations we had more
than a thousand
nominations submitted it turned out that
the top six happened to divide evenly
between
left and right and were far enough away
from their next nearest competitors that
we
had held a ranked choice vote for the
nine possible tickets you could assemble
and our top ticket
ended up being tulsi gabbard and dan
crenshaw
very exciting so something i've noticed
as i've been
researching unity 2020 and watching your
live streams is that at the core of this
there seems to be some very strong
principles and that your process
for how this whole thing has been
designed and unfolded
the organizing itself um like what you
just described
about how you even came to select these
candidates is
rooted deeply in these principles and
can you talk a little bit about
uh the principles at the core of this
cultural movement
and how that is kind of uh the core
motivation
for what you're doing with unity 2020
sure
i think there are really two principles
one is we're doomed
and two is that's bad so anyway this is
an attempt to avoid doom
because it's uh it's what we're built
for and
in some sense you know if i put the
jokes aside
the people who are drawn to the movement
really do believe that the republic is
in
grave danger and that the
collapse or disintegration of the
republic would be a huge
setback not just for americans but for
people across
the west and possibly the whole world
because in some sense the power vacuum
that would be created by
the collapse of the u.s would open the
door
to regressive regimes and
was really potentially an existential
threat to
to our way of life
absolutely so there's also um
criticism about the movement you know uh
not
going to be able to like achieve its
stated goals
but i think what is interesting about
how
at the core there is what i see you
advocating for
is is patriotism principled action
is thinking about the bigger picture you
know and
putting oneself forth for something that
we you know believe in
rather than thinking about um you know
what is what is the most likely
you know chance that we have so
thinking about this regardless of the
outcome of the 2020 election
which is a bet at this point for all of
us what do you think
the value of getting involved
aggressively
in this movement um besides what
specifically happens on november 3rd
well i'm really glad you asked that
question because
the proposal has always had two
components
one is a an emergency plan for
the current election and the other
is the larger recognition that what
unites us
is far greater and more important than
what divides us and that is being lost
by virtue of various processes you know
a failure of sense-making which
i think still is very deliberately built
to counteract
so those processes are
destructive of many things most
centrally is the recognition that we are
actually in
the same boat and we are dependent on
our recognition of that fact to to
continue
so um you know we can talk about unity
2020 the plan for
this election and we can talk about the
overarching dynamic of unity what i
would call the unity movement
and i would say the former is a
manifestation of the latter but the
latter is the much more important
fact
great so can you talk can you talk a
little bit more about unity you know
we're here for unity 2020 but
what is the unity movement and what is
the broader
uh plan beyond even just the next month
of organizing for
for the election what's the big picture
here
well so the first thing to say is that i
announced this proposal on joe rogan and
people
just started showing up which was
in and of itself telling right there was
a great hunger for somebody to speak
to something beyond politics and i think
there was a second
piece to it which was if i was a
centrist by nature
then it wouldn't be very interesting
that i was advocating for something
that um sidelined the duopoly by
navigating the space between it but
because i'm actually a radical
people heard somebody putting aside
their own ideology
in favor of something more important and
it caused many of them to do the same
thing
so i would say the most telling feature
is that we have this uh large
network of volunteers people who are
spending a tremendous amount
of time on the unity project and they're
very good folks
and we gather and we talk about what to
do and we scratch our heads over
all of the twists and turns of 2020
and the fact is i couldn't tell you
which side of the aisle most of them are
on
i actually just don't know because it is
um
such an unimportant fact in the context
of people who have gathered together
in a patriotic effort to save the
republic
that it just doesn't come up
that's beautiful um the other thing that
you've been doing which is
organizing all of this within the
context of a pandemic
so all of these you know other ways of
kind of
you know rallying political support of
having big events and
you know having speakers and having all
of these people coming together and
being in the energy of a movement
are not accessible to you and so you've
been relying very heavily on
on online platforms and i know that
you've had difficulty
uh getting your message through on
twitter
um can you talk about that what's going
on with twitter
and the censorship that's happening
there sure
so first of all i would say that the um
the constraints that come along with
kovid
are a mixed bag because on the one hand
it does mean that there are lots of
things we would like to do that we can't
on the other hand it has put everybody
in the frame of mind of breaking
whatever rules they thought
accompanied what must take place in the
context of a campaign or anything else
and you know people are figuring out new
ways to exist and
some of that is counterproductive but i
think in large measure just the fact
that we all have to think
consciously about how to interact rather
than be on autopilot
is very productive with respect to the
platforms
this is also revealing just how much
power they have
not over not only over whether or not we
have access and can
talk to our our followers and attract
new ones
but um you know how we think
right because the the hidden feature of
these things are the algorithms at their
core
that actually adjust what it is that
comes through your feed
and you know which voices are amplified
and which ones are dampened and so
what we ran into in the context of
twitter is actually fascinating
the first thing i'll say about it is
that we categorize it inside the
movement
as the flack you get when you're over
the target in other words the fact that
we're getting this pushback is not good
the pushback is dangerous but
the fact that we are getting it is an
indication that we've struck a nerve and
that's something
that if we weren't doing it we'd have to
wonder if we were
on a pointless mission so what happened
was
we had an account that was the central
distribution point for information about
unity
it was the articles of unity account on
twitter and
we advanced a hashtag on the last day of
the republican convention
just say no to donald and joe and
we broadcasted over that channel and our
vast network of volunteers broadcast the
hashtag and it spread and actually we
succeeded in getting that hashtag to
trend
next thing we knew our account was
suspended
no indication of why many of our
detractors who have accused us of all
kinds of things
were crowing on twitter about having
reported us
um for various malfeasance including
being russian bots
and um we were unable to get anything
official out of twitter about
what it was that they were claiming we
had done but back channel
we were told that we had registered
something like 50 fake accounts
in order to amplify the hashtag now that
did not ring true to us but because it's
a large
volunteer organization we had to check
very thoroughly to make sure there was
nothing that we were unaware of that
some
uh overzealous volunteer had engaged in
after a week of exhaustive interviews of
people who were part of our movement
and checking everything that was
possible to check it became very clear
that whatever twitter thought had
happened
had not and we filed an appeal
and we have heard nothing back
just silence i should also point out
that
in the early phases of the suspension it
was impossible to post
a link to our website no person on
twitter
could link to our website if you
attempted it the tweet did not go
through and you got a message that said
that the website might
contain harmful information now mind you
this is a group of patriots attempting
to escape the duopoly
who are resolutely non-ideological
and above politics now twitter
could have many opinions about that but
the idea that it feels entitled to block
other people from posting links to our
website tells you something
about the arrogance inside the
organization
so i'm not sure exactly what we can do
about any of this because
of course the platforms have a
tremendous amount of discretion
they dodge and weave between the
interpretations that they are publishers
and they are platforms taking the
advantages of both positions and the
disadvantages of neither
and unfortunately they effectively
own what is now the public square
through
pure technological accident and that
means
that we have no ability to reach each
other
without their okay and
anyway it's a very serious concern that
we ought to focus on collectively
irrespective of where we find ourselves
in the political dialogue a threat to
speech
that comes in the form of mysterious
algorithms
and uh un uh unaccountable
judges is simply unacceptable
yeah that's deeply concerning has unity
the unity movement or unity 2020
integrated this experience
and made it part of the platform itself
to talk about tech and
and media um involvement in in our
political
discourse you know i would say we're in
touch with many
of the people you would imagine we
should talk to about this
in terms of figuring out how to
integrate it
into the movement i would say it
actually points to the larger
question you asked before unity
is it is a movement about
obstacles to good governance so
there are many things that are obstacles
to good governance corruption
is one uh the
perverse incentives that accompany the
platforms that allow us to talk to each
other
is another and we effectively
oppose all such things and let me give
you a a modern example so you have a
better sense of what i'm talking about
so ruth bader ginsburg's death creates
a number of problems in addition to
being
just simply very sad it raises the
specter
that an election that many people
already expect to be
contested might run into an additional
hazard which is to say
a court of eight can deadlock 50 50
whereas a court of
nine cannot and so her absence means
that we might be faced with a situation
in which the supreme court
has to rescue the republic and is
incapable of doing so
so in that context it seems
patriotically true
that we should do everything all those
who view
the survival of the republic as
paramount
should seek to seat a proper justice as
quickly as possible
the president should nominate someone
who is not
divisive and the senate should speed
their confirmation
so that at the point we reach the
election we have all the tools available
to save ourselves from some sort of an
ambiguous
and dangerous outcome so in the unity
movement
i feel we would be wise to advocate such
a thing we don't regard that as
political
now many on the left will regard it as
political because they see
blocking the nomination as their
obligation in light of what happened in
but we see it differently and we are
very likely to advocate for the
rapid seating of a good justice in short
order
so you have just over a month
before the election how are you going to
use
this very precious time uh to accelerate
the movement
and to grow interest and um
yeah what are you what are you going to
do well if i can be
candid with you i think we are
in the following predicament so were it
true
that upon announcing this a groundswell
has
had emerged we could have drafted our
candidates and we could have
imposed on the parties that have ballot
access to partner with us and that was
the plan
now we saw a very good growth but we did
not see
a groundswell in fact i think many
people are still traumatized by the long
abusive relationship that they've had
with the duopoly
and find themselves sitting on the fence
maybe rooting for us but not willing to
say out loud that they're actually
entertaining
the possibility that we could do
something
so in that light the path
to the white house has become pretty
unlikely
now it could still happen right we still
have the debates ahead of us
and both the major party candidates
are rather old we're talking about two
septuaginarians we don't
know what will happen in these debates
but it is possible that something
will cause a shift in the electorate
where suddenly one side will realize
that its ticket
is not actually viable and it will fear
the election of the other
that could put this plan in motion right
there are actually pathways to the
election of the unity ticket right up to
the point of the election
but that would require
something of historic proportions to
unfold in very short order
absent such a thing i would say the
focus has to be
on the movement going forward and
i think we are in grave jeopardy in the
short term
i personally am
i hesitate to use the term frightened
but i don't think there's really a good
alternative i'm frightened about what's
going to happen
if the election is anything but clear
i'm frightened that one side or the
other will not accept the results that
violence will occur
and that it will further deepen the
divide that is
threatening us and so in some sense
i'm not sure we have till 2024 um
but i would say the odds
are uh better than 50 50 that we will
make it to 2024.
there's nothing on the horizon that
suggests it's going to cure the basic
problem of uh divisive partisan politics
and therefore we have to be ready
for next time and frankly with this much
run-up we can be in a much better
position where for example we don't have
to impose on
third parties for ballot access if this
is the path forward
then we could gain ballot access through
the uh the normal mechanisms normal
mechanisms which i should point out the
duopoly
has made onerous for reasons of
self-protection
right so we're about to move over to the
audience q a is there anything else that
you want to
just say before we move into the dynamic
part of the live podcast
well i should say i feel a little weird
uh with
you asking these questions i don't think
people fully grasp
that um to say that you were a student
of mine
is really you know this is this does not
properly characterize how well we know
each other because
you in addition to being my student for
a number of
years were present on the
trip that my wife and i ran
to ecuador in our second to last year of
teaching at evergreen
so we've been in the field together in
fact
if i'm remembering correctly you and i
were almost killed together in the same
storm
as a result of a sudden tree fall right
so anyway
it's good to see you raven and
um anyway i just feel that context is
necessary to know because uh i don't
know
it'd be weird to imagine that we just
sort of we're in the same classroom
no i mean yes they're a lot together
yep very true yeah and it's
changed my life to know you that's
definitely the case
yes oh okay
and with that let us move to
the q a so if you have a question for
brett go ahead throw it in the chat
this is not the opportunity to debate
him so
you get your question and then a
follow-up question
you feel called to do that um and we're
gonna begin
with david
would you like to unmute yourself and
ask your question
yeah thank you very much hey thanks fred
um
yeah i've been following along so i know
that you've reached out to the
libertarian
parties jergensen um and it's
understandable that she
she's reluctant to hand you the unity 20
20 um
seat for the nomination that she
received but is it conceivable that um
the green party and the libertarian
parties and the unity movement could get
together for
some way to combine forces to make a
third-party option really
really viable so that um
whether it's a debate between them
that would show intelligence distinct
from the
candidates or some other method where
they they could
in a sense combine efforts and say unity
would support the libertarians if
if some contest showed that among the
three of them
the one that had the best chances of
winning would be
any one of those three a great question
i would say there are a lot of ways it
could go um
there is so to our mind we were not
exactly asking the libertarians and or
greens and or any other of the third
party options
to hand us their ballot access we were
hoping that they would recognize this as
a real opportunity
because what happens with the third
parties
is they attain the status
of historical footnote at best
at worst they get enough of the vote to
be blamed
for whoever is elected
and in this case what we were suggesting
was that if they were to step aside
for one election cycle that there would
be
a lot of value for their long-term
well-being and the value would come in a
couple of different forms
first for any party that gets
five percent of the vote there are
federal funds
available in a future election had one
of the parties achieve five percent in
the past election
that would have been worth 20 million
dollars in this case
so we're talking about a large
bit of fuel that was available to a
third party that had the vision
to partner with us also
our vote that we held between our nine
possible tickets was a ranked choice
vote which is evidence of our commitment
to the idea of rank choice voting and
rank choice voting
is probably the key proposal
to increase the influence of third
parties
in our governance so
what we were hoping was that they would
recognize that this was a long-term
investment and that
in effect they were making a trade
rather than uh
engaging in charity now i don't
actually know what the conversation
sounds like on the inside of these
parties
i do know that we are in contact with
people
in the libertarian organization we had
justin amash on our most recent
campfire and
so i think there is a kind of dawning
awareness in these circles that there's
a larger
a larger game theoretic puzzle to be
solved
now as to the particular structure you
lay out
i think there are some game theoretic
problems with it
in other words the libertarians and the
greens for example
because these are ideology-based parties
um have to swallow a very bitter pill
if they are to team up in order to
defeat the duopoly but are to empower
something that is distant from
themselves ideologically
that is probably not a viable structure
which is exactly why the unity proposal
looks the way it does
by being non-ideological it allows those
of us who recognize that the corruption
in our system is the hazard to it
serving our collective well-being it
allows us to gather together under one
banner and
not be compromised in so doing
just a quick follow-up just i think it's
a yes or no is there just a sense that
if it were to further the third party
option
could you see i mean obviously you can't
guarantee anybody
does anything could you see encouraging
the unity followers
to back the libertarians if there was
some way that that actually would be
more viable for making third party
option bible this time
well again i think it's a larger game
theoretic puzzle
what we will certainly do is we will
advocate that people vote their
conscience
to the extent that the argument is you
mustn't consider
voting for anything other than the major
party options because
you'll elect the greater evil i would
remind you
once upon a time mitt romney was the
greater evil
that tells you how dumb this argument is
right people are now begging for a mitt
romney-like figure they're wishing
that such a person would step in and
save us from the absurd
choice that the duopoly has stuck us
with but
you know in the past this was an
unthinkable fate
so that's the argument the argument is
false
people should vote their conscience and
if they did we wouldn't be stuck with
the structure
thank you we're going to go to paul
dunscombe
would you like to mute yourself and ask
a question
hey um so from my perspective at c
and i'm sure a lot of others it seems
like the two tribes
live in sort of two different realities
which to me seems
fundamentally different than having two
different ideologies
how does unity address this
epistemological crisis
and and second how does the answer not
just be a split the difference where
neither
side is happy all right
um that is multifaceted but you're
exactly right
now i would argue that the distinct
and maybe more importantly
unreconcilable
narratives exist in service of a
structure that does not wish to be
displaced by
analysis and its logical consequences
so the two tribes do live in
what i see as an almost reciprocal
pair of realities so the way i used to
say this
is the fox news viewer
sees the npr listener as insane the npr
listener
regards the the fox news viewer as crazy
and they're both right
right so they they each see something in
the other that is accurate and causes
them not to pay attention and what they
don't see
is the same distortion in themselves and
so
first thing to say is those who have
arrived
at a unity orientation and my guess is
i'm looking at a screen full of people
who have
something like a unity orientation that
those people begin to recognize that the
truth
is not encapsulated in either place
that it is it has to be constructed
all a cart because it is actually
complex
so um what are we doing about it i think
that's almost
the wrong way to look at it i would say
many different projects aim to solve a
piece of this puzzle
unity 2020 aims to
solve this puzzle in the political
context
whereas stoa is aiming to solve this
in a social context idw
aimed to solve it in a sense-making
public context
you know close kin to stella maybe but
all of these things are attempts to
bypass these game theoretic failures
and bootstrap a superior alternative and
what i
hope above all else is that all of these
projects that aim to do that
begin to recognize that they are each
looking at one facet of the same gem
and the extent that we do that we become
very powerful
very quickly
okay all do you have a any kind of
response
no okay let us move
to blaine would you like to
yourself and ask a question
uh yes let me just pull it up all right
i'm just gonna read what i submitted it
says instead of ubi
wouldn't earned universal income be a
platform for
unity basically putin citizens would
serve in the communities for x amount of
time or
x way to earn ubi seems to be two birds
one stone
uh they're saying defund the police but
also have citizens uh service police so
policing gets more resources
to focus on education and training but
also quote unquote defund
as then put back into the communities
through the citizens earning
their ubi
so um
i think this is a very good
this shows us a an important fork
in the conversation so i personally
agree with you about uh what i would
call participation income as
likely superior to universal basic
income
but that conversation really has no
place
in the unity layer right because as much
as i think
that's a desirable thing and that all
reasonable people should probably
be considering some proposal in this
neighborhood as the solution to
a large and growing problem that's my
personal political belief
right what i'm hoping what the
unity proposal is built around is the
idea
that if you put two uh patriots
in a room from different sides of the
political spectrum
and they hash this out in the interest
of the nation
that they will arrive at a good answer
right if the good answer is something
like participation income
i'm hoping that that will be shown by
the process
but i do think it is important to
separate our own political
desires and beliefs from
the effort to rid the system of the
corruption that prevents a rational set
of beliefs from guiding us
uh thank you uh yeah i just
from that platform i kind of view it as
also
uh the members serving uh
through the earned ubi um program
could also be kind of giving the people
a big brother into
all of the elements of service to
because let's say you have a physical
physical
uh disability it can only serve through
abdication you would still be able to
keep eye
to make sure there's no like corruption
in certain um
departments or anywhere um and
the way i'm gonna cut in here uh thank
you so much for your question but we're
gonna go to megan's question
thank you megan would you like to remit
yourself and ask the question
ah thanks very much um i was curious by
um by uh when you said that uh the power
that sweater has is a technological
accident
um there's a term that i learned here on
the star that um
i was really i think i was really
looking for in life which is the blue
church
um and it looks to me like both twitter
and facebook are branches of that blue
church
um they they are very specific
in the in the angle that they push i'm
noticing the flags that say um learn how
voting by mail is safe and secure it's
like it's a very very specific message
that those people are pushing um
so i was wanting to know what's your
basis for attributing this
this effect to being an accident um
and what would be your opinion on the
implication of the possibility either
that's an accident or that it's actually
a branch of something that is organized
that's that's interesting because i mean
i see exactly the same
bias that you do i do think silicon
valley
is um it is in alignment with the blue
church
but the way i would say it is that
silicon valley
is utilizing one half of the duopoly
to advance its interests and so the
reason that we have
two parties in the duopoly is that there
are actually competing interests within
the elites
and the elites the rent seekers
basically own all of the power
this is why policy has almost
no uh relationship to the desire of the
electorate
the electorate is a
a body that has to be persuaded to award
power which is then monetized
and peddled by these two these two
forces but
they're peddling to different
constituencies right so
you know it might be that um the
the blue church as you put it is uh
in alignment with alternative energy
properties
and that the red religion is
um defending uh fossil fuels and that
those two things are in competition with
each other
but the fact is the corruption that
comes from both of these things pushing
their interests
in this pugilistic context
it's corrosive to us serving our
interests which would have
representatives who don't have
a dog in the fight um talking about what
energy policy should be
going forward so the leap in your
question
is um did
did these platforms um
have an alignment with the blue church
or did they find the blue church the
democratic party as the locale
through which they could corrupt the
system in their interest and i think it
is very much likely to be
the latter the historical accident
is just the fact of the
amazing rate of growth that accompanied
the innovations
in social media and search
those things empowered a group of
companies that started from nothing to
dominate this entire
piece of landscape so that we cannot for
example
simply opt for something that functions
like twitter
but doesn't uh take its view of
censorship
right we are left with either accepting
twitter's view of censorship or opting
out of all twitter-like phenomena
and i let's put it this way the
hypothesis
that this is something more than a
historical accident is something that
would require
some evidence and i haven't seen it yet
it looks to me like
a much more natural story of
um of platforms finding a mechanism to
serve their interests
in a governmental structure that is
prone to
facilitate corruption
i'll just add a quick uh follow-up um
i'm just wondering about the sort of
implication of the equal
the equal basis of the blue and the red
in this case um just my perspective on
this
is maybe a little unusual because i'm a
new zealander and we don't have red
flavored mainstream news
uh we only have blue flavored mainstream
news uh washington
washington coast new york times um are
the
are the outlets that are constantly
repeated in our media
um and there is there is there seems to
be absolutely no equivalent here
and um anyone who gets their narrative
in the mainstream media of the uh you
know the great southern bolt hole over
here
seems to me to um to be i mean that's a
that's it's a very superlative
achievement um
which i guess makes me more more
inclined to believe that it's not some
kind of accident but
sorry i guess that's not really a
question i'll uh i'll um i'll let
someone else take over
i'm going to read this question on
behalf of drew
buckmiller with the stated concern of
gridlock
in the supreme court with an even number
of justices
how does the same concern relate to the
proposal of operating under consensus
between the two people on the unity
ticket
yep great question so first of all
the unity proposal
is built to take our constitutional
structure
and use it in a new way without having
to alter it
right this is a model that i would
suggest we need to get
better at right having a constitutional
convention to sit to fix your structure
may seem like the right move but it
could end in disaster
whereas doing something that is
constitutional but unforeseen
doesn't carry the same hazard in this
case
you elect a president and vice president
they informally agree to rule to govern
by consensus
and in the case that they can't reach a
consensus
the president is the president right so
you could regard that as
a major asymmetry but the agreement also
has them reversing roles after four
years and so even if there is
a slight bias within any four year
period
it tends to reverse over time and this
maintains balance
is it perfect no but if you found two
good people
and the two people that we found for the
ticket we hope to draft
tulsi gabbard and dan crenshaw they
actually turn out
to be friends and although ideologically
they're quite far apart
they clearly have um the characteristics
necessary
for them to discuss what should be done
in a humane and decent way with each
other
they also both are clear patriots and so
the interests of the nation
would presumably loom larger for them
than their own
personal desires
chris c would you like to meet yourself
and ask your question
hey brett cruz to know what uh the unity
movement stances on
local and state politics
well so far we have taken no
action with respect to anything down
ballot
that's because we got started very late
in light of a national emergency
that surrounded the presidential ticket
long term
those races are obviously important
and what i would say is we would take
the same
overarching posture which is that
somebody has to advocate
for the well-being you know for the
patriotic middle
unfortunately in the context of some of
these state processes
a mechanism for balance is harder to
build
right the presidential ticket because of
the way president and vice president
are elected allowed us to use this
proposal
you have to be cleverer to make it work
in other contexts that don't lend
themselves to that balance
thank you very much all right let me see
here
listen would you like to ask the
question
sure thank you i'm here i was pulling
over
okay hi thank you brett my question is
do you see any glimpses
yet of other projects or campaigns
being started initiated by the unity
2020 team or movement
um in addition to the political campaign
that
has started it all well
let me understand your question you're
asking if people
inside the unity movement are starting
their own initiatives
yeah other projects initiatives even if
it's just a glimpse or a sense of
something that might be created or
produced by those individuals as a
result of this
there's lots of discussion inside the
movement about what to do
and how to move forward um
i think the thing that troubles me and
this isn't the first time i've seen it
so you all are presumably familiar with
game b
okay so to the extent that you are
familiar with game b game b
was at a time back in
2013-ish it was a group of people who
met
to discuss the question of how
to transition civilization to something
more effective
less fragile and more humane
in any case early in that process
we had a fair amount of discussion over
whether or not
we were the only effort
to discuss that systematically the only
people meeting or were there a thousand
rooms of people meeting having parallel
discussions
and the answer adjusts things rather
radically
if game b had been one of a thousand
groups
targeted at that same puzzle then at
some in some sense
only one has to succeed right if game b
was the only one of those then it had to
succeed and those
uh knowing the answer to that causes you
to play the game differently
i think we discovered over time that in
the english-speaking world
there were not a thousand game bees in
fact the
tendency was for those things that began
to show signs of thinking in this
direction
that they tended to coalesce and that's
probably not a good thing
probably from the point of view of our
over all well-being
we should want to see many separate
projects that do not
fail together now in the case of unity
again i would imagine
in the context of a presidential
election with two unforgivably bad
tickets that you would imagine lots of
people
would be generating alternative
mechanisms some of them
more cogent than others but you would
expect to see lots of
projects like that and we saw very
little that was new
so that worries me what that tells me is
that somehow we've gotten into
the habit of thinking this is impossible
and at the same time i would argue that
logically it is necessary
so if we all imagine that that which is
necessary is actually impossible and it
paralyzes
us so we don't do it we're in serious
trouble
so anyway i'd love to see lots of other
unity-themed
movements arise and then we could talk
about whether
teaming up made sense or you know
honorably competing with each other made
sense or some hybrid of the two
but at the moment what i see is uh
we tried it and we don't see a lot of
other attempts and that
is probably not good news
thank you
all right let's move to james baker
hi thanks um so this is a question about
polarization and
maybe avoiding but more recovering uh so
thinking forward
to maybe 2024 or down the road um
when if and when unity is embraced a bit
more
by one party than the other uh
what i see happening there is then
instantly it would become
part of the polarized frame like it
would get polarized in the frame of
everybody from both tribes
how would what would the strategy then
be to kind of recover from that
um to be very careful what you agreed to
right so yes i can imagine that at some
point
the major parties might realize that
they
had something to gain by capturing unity
and unity has to be uncapturable and it
doesn't mean
that we wouldn't be willing to play ball
with a a major party but the point is
each choice has to be one
that is safe to engage in and that is
justified on its merits
so in essence we would have to have
the ability to pull one of the parties
in the direction
of the patriotic center in order for it
to be worth even contemplating
i guess my follow-up would be to relate
this back to the general dynamic of
third parties
um and how to
like the the you said something about
like avoid
um you know being captured
uh but um sorry the
the impulse here like if if uh if
adopted by
one side more than the other like how do
you
how do you avoid being captured when the
thing that is the capturing is the frame
of everybody in both tribes who is
looking at this thing
and trying to decide whether it's
something that they can trust
to navigate that knife's edge
third-party route or
or whether it just becomes part of the
tribal warfare
the answer is first principles thinking
right if you are reasoning from first
principles and your reasoning
is robust then you are not vulnerable
to being lured into dangerous
illogic now you can still make an error
but the problem
of capture arises when you're
in a a different modality like
one of negotiation where you could
surrender
the peace that you need to hold because
you
it seemed like you were making a trade
that was valuable
so i would just say the unity movement
mustn't do anything that doesn't make
sense on its merits
independent of whether or not it's on
offer
right rob hart would you like to
meet yourself and ask a question
yes i'm scrolling back to find it and
you know um
so the offer from the major parties has
never been worse
uh which means that the potential for a
third party win has never been better um
but two-thirds of americans now agree
that a third party is actually necessary
kind of makes this moment one to
leverage
could unity do that by promising to
reform elections themselves
such that third parties will have a
viable future well in some sense
we're doing that the one thing we
haven't done is start a third party
at the moment unity is a movement now it
might have to become
a third party in order to accomplish
that but
by setting it in motion as a movement we
retained options that i think were
valuable at least
in this initial run-up so from my
perspective
i don't need it to be a third party it
could be a third party and i could be
comfortable with that
what i need is for something to fix the
system so that it stops parasitizing us
and putting us in jeopardy
and i think the statistics that you cite
reflect
the fact that a lot of people are of
similar minds so yes the opportunity is
absolutely
immense and it's much greater even than
most people realize because
there is this huge group of non-voters
and there's a way in which non-voter has
a kind of sound to it where we hear it
as
apathetic but some of the people who
don't vote are apathetic
many of them are disaffected and are
responding to the fact
that the system does not does not react
to their will
those people can easily be brought back
if something does become responsive and
in fact we've seen
a quarter of our volunteers are people
who weren't planning to vote in this
election
until unity so it does mobilize people
who were
interested but not participating
and that group could actually make
a third party or a movement the largest
political force
in the country very quickly
just a follow-up to that um since you
mentioned
that you don't have an interest in
forming a third party i actually feel
that it may be more attractive to people
because they don't feel that this party
or this
movement is seeking its own power but
rather seeking to empower all people
um my thought would be that um
leveraging that that very idea would
allow more people to get on board but
but you point to uh to the thing that
probably is the biggest obstacle to this
and that's
that people don't believe it's possible
so
if they were to reflect on just how
great their numbers are they might
actually see
the movement worthwhile oh
exactly and in a year like 2020
you know people's sense of what is and
isn't possible
is more or less incoherent right because
all this took right this could actually
happen
if people suspended their disbelief but
the fact of
democracy requires that anyway right we
need people
to go and vote in numbers large enough
that their
will is proportionally represented even
though
those people know that their vote
is almost certainly not going to change
any outcome
right so they have already suspended
their disbelief just simply to
participate
and all we're suggesting is actually
suspend your disbelief
in a different direction something
you've been told can't happen
actually can happen and the people who
told you it couldn't happen
have a perverse incentive to lead you to
be paralyzed
great and aaron would you like to bring
us home
with your final question
gladly raven thank you um brett you
mentioned that unity 2020
the idw and the stoa might represent
different facets
of the same jewel how can these
different facets best support each other
how should a platform like the stoa
excuse me what should a platform like to
stowa do in the next month
and how might it evolve between now and
great question first thing to do is just
figure out whether you agree with the
premise
right if you agree with the premise that
these things are manifestations
of the same impulse to make things
better
right to escape the game theoretic traps
of our current system
then i would say first of all spreading
that message
is key right people we are
wasting our effort by being divided you
know
part of its useful division right you
need to have people focused on a problem
that's tractable and if we're all
focused on the total problem it's not
tractable
but to recognize that we are fellow
travelers
empowers us greatly and let me just say
you know it's not just idw stoa game b
unity it's also the makers movement
it's open source right it's all of these
different attempts
to do something uh basically to
restructure incentives so that things
work it's
probably the crypto movement as well so
recognizing the connection is key
spreading the message so that people who
are you know have their blinders on in
their corner of this
realize that they are in some sense part
of something
larger and that it doesn't take very
much to
you know append to your toolkit well
maybe i'm
a you know i'm a programmer and i'm
involved in the open source movement
but i'm also subject to the political
will of the electorate and there is a
parallel project over an electoral space
so whatever effort i put into thinking
about politics i'm going to
tune into that or from the point of view
of sense-making about the world i'm
going to tune into channels that seem to
be dedicated to breaking
these uh toxic narratives that so many
people are being jerked around by
so um i'm not sure that i've given you a
very clear answer
but the recognition that these things
are connected um
to the extent that one can spread that
message so that people who
are likely to have ears to hear because
they're in one of these other projects
can begin to tune in and recognize that
they may have been you know missing a
solution to a problem they weren't even
paying attention to
those things i think will have a very
positive effect in the long term
great thank you and we have reached
our our hour mark um so before we close
brad
where can we find you do you have any
final words that you want to leave us
with um
sure uh let's just say this has been a
great conversation i do feel like i have
stepped into
a um a parallel universe of fellow
travelers
and that's always a very reassuring
thing to discover
people can find they can find
our website for unity2020 at
articlesofunity.org
if you want updates on twitter you can
follow
my twitter account at brettweinstein
brett has1t
you can find my wife and me doing
bi-weekly
podcasts on the dark horse podcast on
youtube or whatever your favorite
podcast app is
and maybe that's that's it
excellent i think i can speak for
everyone thank you so much for being
here this was a really great
conversation
we hope to see you again at the stoa
thank you i really
had a great time and it was nice seeing
you again
and anyway be well all um
let's keep fighting the good fight
absolutely
great and peter i don't know where you
are but do you want to
promote any future events yes uh
so uh brett raven thank you for uh
having that dialogue and thank you
everyone for your excellent questions
some upcoming events uh our boy tyson
has an event coming up
tyson if you can meet yourself and plug
that
sure thank you peter thanks again brett
thank you raven uh tonight at 8 30
eastern is flowing with unknowingness
where we practice
deepening our relationship with
uncertainty and exercising
our trust muscles through freestyle
spoken word and freestyle rap
imagine collective dialogue backed by
hip-hop beats
that's what it is so we'd love to see
you there um
and if you are feeling a little bit
nervous about it i'll just say like all
the more reason
to show up and enjoy it so see you there
tyson's venting a new genre of sense
making rap so uh
must check that out uh tomorrow we have
surrendered leadership with john
thompson he's from circling uh europe
and so we're going to get our kind of
authentic relating circling on that's at
12 p.m eastern time
and susan blackmore um the medic scholar
she's coming in thursday i believe
conscious of selfish jeans and
selfish jeans and memes uh machines
that's september 24th at 12 p.m
eastern time we've got tons of events
check out our website
a lot of exciting action here and if
you'd like to support us while we steal
the culture you can do so on patreon
that being said uh brett raven everyone
thank you so much for coming to pistol
today
well everybody